by the end of this video you'll have a
basic understanding of everything that
you need to know to convert the sun's
energy through your solar panels into
power that you can use in your everyday
life whether that's on grid or off-grid
the first and probably most important
part of any system is the solar panels
themselves these come in a huge variety
of sizes powers and efficiencies like
this panel right here for example
produces up to 395 watts but this one
that's almost the same size produces
only 250 watts at best and no that's not
because it's shattered it actually works
quite well despite being shattered it
just doesn't have the same capacity as
the newer nicer ones now the more power
they produce per area the more they tend
to cost which could be a factor if you
have limited space on your roof or
wherever it is that you're placing the
panels there are also portable panels
like these but they tend to produce a
lot less power they are however great
for portability and for lower power
needs like charging a phone i'd say the
two main things to consider when looking
at solar panels are the wattage output
and also just making sure you've got the
right voltage and nowadays you can also
buy what are called bifacial panels like
this one that even if the back is at all
uncovered they absorb light from the
back adding up to as much as 30 percent
power output i set this one up so that
it's not actually getting any direct
sunlight but it's still collecting power
from both the front and the back and
producing about 39 watts of power not
too shabby the second ingredient is
inverters now inverters can either be up
with the panels and these are called
micro inverters or they can be
downstream where all of the panel's
wires are collected in what's called a
string inverter and you can even use
both their job is simply to convert the
dc power that comes from the panels to
ac power that we can use for our devices
and appliances micro inverters typically
connect to between two and four
photovoltaic panels or these solar
panels and they make it really easy to
expand or condense if you need to your
system you can add monitoring systems to
these but they do have to be serviced up
on the roof and typically underneath the
solar panels so they can be challenging
to get to now because micro inverters
handle power in smaller groups if
certain panels are shaded or under
producing it typically has less of an
impact on the total power production
string inverters bring all of the panel
wiring into a central location and they
have a specific size rating in order to
accommodate up to a certain number of
panels based on wattage and voltage now
if you have to set your panels up in
series to accommodate your string
inverter your panels will only be as
productive as your least productive
panel though power optimizers can help
with that it's also possible to use a
combination of micro inverters and
string inverters if that makes sense for
your setup now it's worth noting that
certain string inverters actually
require a battery to work since they're
designed for off-grid situations so be
sure to check out those details before
you buy another major consideration when
choosing between micro inverters and
string inverters is whether or not you
want the ability to reroute power to
your house during a power outage to do
that you need to disconnect it from the
grid like we can do with this setup this
can allow us to keep our freezers
running in a couple of lights on for
example in case of a blackout now not
all inverters allow for that especially
when you're looking at micro inverters
now let's pause for a second to explain
series versus parallel because that's
something you definitely need to
understand when connecting batteries and
panels so series when you connect
something in series that means the
positive of one panel or battery is
connected to the negative of the next
this puts them all in line with each
other and you can think of it like a tv
series there are certain tv series where
if you skip them or go out of order
you're gonna get totally lost so you
actually need to watch them in order
episode one episode two three and so on
this is also how the old christmas
lights were set up which was super
annoying one bulb would go out you're
not sure which one it is and none of
them worked and it's just horrible so
with parallel on the other hand you're
connecting every positive line together
and every negative line together so you
can pull one out of the mix and it
really won't matter it won't affect the
rest of them the other big thing to know
about series versus parallel is how the
power gets added up so the difference
between series in parallel is one will
add up the volts of each and the other
one will add up the amps of each now in
trying to come up with a good way to
memorize this i decided to use the word
suave and if you think about the letters
and break them down you can say in
series you add volts of each so in this
case with the series the amps stay the
same if you put for example two 250 volt
10 amp panels together in series they'll
produce an output of 500 volts and still
that same 10 amps now the opposite is
true for parallel these same two panels
will produce the original 250 volts but
also 20 amps of power this is really
important in how you connect batteries
this inverter for example can handle 24
volts so i've connected these two 12
volt batteries in series that means it's
adding up their voltage to produce 24
volts and then the amp hours stay the
same which in this case is 150 amp hours
this other inverter on the other hand is
a 12 volt inverter so i connected these
two 12 volt batteries in parallel that
means they still add up to only 12 volts
but they give me double the amp hours so
300 amp hours
it's also very common to mix and match
series in parallel to meet your needs
but no matter what type of circuit you
go with you do need to understand the
output that you'll get as a result now i
totally understand that some of this can
get pretty overwhelming which is why i'm
trying to keep a little bit high level
here and i'm not going too far into some
of the details but if you're just
overwhelmed by the idea of understanding
all that goes into solar and especially
doing it yourself there are some great
options out there for you now this video
is in no way sponsored but i do want to
tell you that there are options out
there that can save you a lot of money
and still be a high quality installation
as i've done my research and looking at
my system that's almost 7 years old i
wish i had the options that are out
there today and when i look around one
of the best options i see is actually
going with tesla which does very similar
systems to what i've got here but they
do it for a lot lower price than what i
paid so i've got a coupon in the
description that you can use to save 300
off any installation it's just a
referral code it helps me out and it
saves you a few bucks too so if you're
interested in doing something that's not
diy that's a great option that you can
check out they actually have a
configurator right on their site that
you can put everything in see what the
cost will be for you see what the loan
options are versus paying it out of
pocket all that good stuff so feel free
to check that out if that's something
that you're interested in having said
that let's explain the rest of this
system so you can see how this all comes
together now just as a reminder all
electrical work that you do of this
nature should definitely be checked by a
certified electrician and then you need
to make sure to adhere to all local
guidelines local codes and whatever it
is that your town tells you to do with
solar in your area all right on to our
third ingredient which is switches and
safety measures now there are several
different versions of these so here i've
got a pv combiner which is just a really
nice box with fuses and switches to be
able to allow you to connect multiple
solar panels to one output you can also
use circuit breakers there are
disconnects involved both dc and ac
there are fuses and each of these
basically serves two purposes the first
and the one they all do is they create a
break point between one portion of your
system and the next they make it easy to
disable power to a section so that you
can service it now the second one that
almost all of these do is they also
provide protection from surges and
overloads an electrical code requires
these in certain locations but it's
always best to err on the side of having
too many in place for safety sake the
only one of these that does not provide
any overload protection is the
disconnect boxes those really are just
an on off switch that you can use now
when it comes to deciding how much power
you need to generate with your solar
system consider this analogy imagine you
have no running water at your home but
you do have a water tank out back you
also have a large opening on the top of
the tank to collect that water but it
only rains for about four hours per day
now you've got a water pump that pushes
the water from your tank to your house
so that you can actually use it now in
this analogy the tank is your battery
system the opening to the tank is your
solar panel array and the pump is your
inverter if you're not getting enough
rain into your tank you need a bigger
opening to collect the rain which means
more solar panels if you're not getting
enough water from the tank to your home
you need a bigger or better pump which
is in this case a better inverter and if
you're using more water than is in your
tank you need a bigger tank which is a
bigger battery system on that note let's
talk about batteries which is the fourth
ingredient in our recipe there's a ton
to cover with batteries so we won't get
into all of it but there are several
kinds of batteries out there that can be
used to store power from a solar panel
system for later use if you're building
a grid tied system you don't actually
need to use batteries unless you want to
add protection against power outages you
can use a tesla power wall for this or
you can use your own batteries if you
are building an off-grid system however
batteries are essential for power
storage just like with solar panels
these can be combined for additional
storage in addition to solution like the
batteries that we've shown here as well
as the tesla power wall there are even
certain electric vehicles coming out
that claim to be able to power your
house like the ford f-150 lightning says
it can power your house off the ford's
battery to provide power for up to as
much as a few days which would be pretty
awesome so i'm sure we'll see a lot more
of that sort of thing coming out over
the next several years batteries do have
a voltage rating like six volt 12 volt
or 24 volt typically they also have
different amp hours kilowatt hours cycle
count efficiencies temperature ratings
and more to compare so we won't get into
all of that for now but i will say that
you do need batteries to store power if
you're not tied to the grid and they're
optional if you are now the last
ingredient is the wiring and connectors
to connect all the pieces together there
is again a lot to get into here but if
you're using wires that are going to be
outside at all they need to be outdoor
rated or you need to use what's called
thhn or thwn wire that goes inside of
the electrical conduit th n wires are
individually sheathed cables that are
rated for exterior use inside a conduit
a cheap alternative to using the solar
specific panel wiring is just to use
some 12 gauge landscape wiring this
actually works really well you just need
to connect your mc4 connections which is
what most solar panels use as their
connector mc4 connectors are great
because they make it really easy to see
that you've got a secure connection
they're weatherproof and you can both
feel and hear when they make that
perfect connection
now for wiring up batteries you usually
need a much heavier gauge wire because
there's more amperage going through so
i'll often use this two gauge wire which
also requires the use of either a 3 8 or
a 5 16 copper lug and then some pretty
heavy duty crimpers to put these
together so those are those five
ingredients now to put those together
we're going to connect the solar panels
to a fuse or a pv combiner box that gets
connected to an inverter and then you
can connect your inverter to either
batteries or the grid for the off-grid
setup this is pretty much the whole
install right here you can connect
outlets to this if you need to but more
typically you'd connect this to a
circuit breaker panel that is completely
non-grid tied for grid tied you would
run wiring from your inverter through an
ac disconnect box and then into your
main circuit breaker panel like this
this provides power to the rest of the
circuit breaker panel and your power
company will install a bi-directional
meter that measures how much power is
coming in from solar versus how much is
being used at your residence with that
you've got working power to run your
appliances and devices directly from the
sun's rays how awesome is that i'm nils
with learn to diy thanks for watching